<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<XMLDocContent PageName="SupportLibraries.AudioStream.AudioStream.PlayBuffer" Title="PlayBuffer method" xmlns="http://www.exodusemulator.com/schema/XMLDocSchema.xsd">
  <Section Title="Description">
    <Paragraph>
      This method sends a previously allocated <PageRef PageName="SupportLibraries.AudioStream.AudioStream.AudioBuffer">AudioBuffer</PageRef> object
      for playback. The caller is responsible for filling the AudioBuffer object with valid sample data before calling this method. Note that the
      caller is also responsible for handling sample rate conversion issues. When a buffer is sent for playback, it must match the sample rate being
      used for the audio output device. If sample rate conversion is required, the caller must perform this sample rate conversion. This is best
      achieved by using the <PageRef PageName="SupportLibraries.AudioStream.AudioStream.ConvertSampleRate">ConvertSampleRate</PageRef> function to
      adjust the sample rate of the raw sample data.
    </Paragraph>
    <Paragraph>
      Note that audio buffers should be sent for playback in the order they are created. If two AudioBuffer objects are allocated by successive calls
      to the <PageRef PageName="SupportLibraries.AudioStream.AudioStream.CreateAudioBuffer">CreateAudioBuffer</PageRef> method, and the second buffer
      is sent for playback through a call to the PlayBuffer method, that buffer will not begin playback until the first buffer is either sent for
      playback too, or deleted through a call to the <PageRef PageName="SupportLibraries.AudioStream.AudioStream.DeleteAudioBuffer">DeleteAudioBuffer</PageRef>
      method.
    </Paragraph>
  </Section>
  <Section Title="Usage">
    <Code><![CDATA[void PlayBuffer(AudioBuffer* buffer);]]></Code>
    <SubSection Title="Argument list">
      <ArgumentList>
        <ArgumentListEntry Type="AudioBuffer*!SupportLibraries.AudioStream.AudioStream.AudioBuffer" Name="buffer">
          The AudioBuffer object to send for playback
        </ArgumentListEntry>
      </ArgumentList>
    </SubSection>
  </Section>
  <Section Title="See also">
    <PageRefList>
      <PageRefListEntry PageName="SupportLibraries.AudioStream.AudioStream">AudioStream class</PageRefListEntry>
      <PageRefListEntry PageName="SupportLibraries.AudioStream.AudioStream.CreateAudioBuffer">CreateAudioBuffer method</PageRefListEntry>
      <PageRefListEntry PageName="SupportLibraries.AudioStream.AudioStream.DeleteAudioBuffer">DeleteAudioBuffer method</PageRefListEntry>
    </PageRefList>
  </Section>
</XMLDocContent>

