<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<XMLDocContent PageName="SupportLibraries.Image" Title="Image Support Library" xmlns="http://www.exodusemulator.com/schema/XMLDocSchema.xsd">
  <Section Title="Description">
    <Paragraph>
      The Image library is designed to simplify working with graphical images. The <PageRef PageName="SupportLibraries.Image.Image">Image</PageRef>
      class is provided by this library, which allows images to be created and edited, and saved to or loaded from a variety of image formats. The
      <PageRef PageName="SupportLibraries.Image.IImage">IImage</PageRef> interface is provided to allow Image objects to be easily shared between
      assemblies.
    </Paragraph>
    <Paragraph>
      This library is split into two halves, Image and ImageInterface. This allows code which only needs to use Image objects, not create them, to
      include only the header files required to work with the object. This reduces code linkage, encourages the use of the interface base types, and
      reduces compilation types and assembly sizes.
    </Paragraph>
  </Section>

  <Section Title="Public Members">
    <SubSection Title="ImageInterface Members">
      <PageRefList>
        <PageRefListEntry PageName="SupportLibraries.Image.IImage">IImage</PageRefListEntry>
      </PageRefList>
    </SubSection>
    <SubSection Title="Image Members">
      <PageRefList>
        <PageRefListEntry PageName="SupportLibraries.Image.Image">Image</PageRefListEntry>
      </PageRefList>
    </SubSection>
  </Section>

  <Section Title="Status of the library">
    <Paragraph>
      The Image library has a number of issues, and there are major changes planned for it in the future.
    </Paragraph>
    <Paragraph>
      The current Image class was built heavily around the idea of loading and displaying images, and not as much around editing and creating them. As
      a result, the Image class is very slow and difficult to work with when actually trying to build image data. There is a future plan to build a
      Canvas class, which will allow advanced drawing operations, with other classes like a Pen, Brush, etc supporting advanced draw operations to it.
      If we create a Canvas class, there may not be any need for a separate Image class type.
    </Paragraph>
    <Paragraph>
      The Image class as it stands also has a major issue around the use of third party libraries. Most of the libraries we include to add support for
      extra image formats are very large, and increase the size of the output assemblies significantly. There should be a way to separate the image
      file load and save routines from the Image class itself. Since that is mostly all that this class does, it makes sense that we would just
      provide a separate class to assist in image loading or saving with image files, and that this class would work with Canvas objects.
    </Paragraph>
    <Paragraph>
      There is a further question around the idea of image sets, or in other words, files which contain multiple images. Icon files are an example of
      this, and it would be extremely useful to support them. It's only a small step from this to animated files like GIF images, or even actual video
      files, with audio tracks. With this in mind, the future of this library is probably as some kind of MediaSupport library, with support for all
      kinds of image and sound data formats, both creation and editing, as well as saving and loading. Any refactor of this library should consider
      this as the logical future direction we should head towards.
    </Paragraph>
  </Section>
</XMLDocContent>
