<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<XMLDocContent PageName="SupportLibraries.Overview" Title="Overview of Support Libraries" xmlns="http://www.exodusemulator.com/schema/XMLDocSchema.xsd">
  <Section Title="Description">
    <Paragraph>
      The support libraries for the Exodus project are libraries that were written to make performing various programming tasks easier, but are technically
      issues outside the bounds of the Exodus project itself. Ideally, none of these libraries would exist as part of this project at all, and would instead
      be provided as part of the C++ STL libraries, or a widely used and accepted set of third party libraries like boost. Where no suitable language or
      third party library has been available to perform a particular task however, or where the solutions provided by them were deemed to be poor, incomplete,
      or too low level for us to use directly within our code, support libraries have been created for use within Exodus. If suitable third party libraries
      or language features are added or identified in the future that could replace a custom support library here, it may be appropriate to deprecate or
      remove that library.
    </Paragraph>
    <Paragraph>
      Note that unlike the <PageRef PageName="Libraries.Overview">Core Libraries</PageRef>, our support libraries do not need to be platform
      independent. In fact, some libraries may exist for the sole purpose of assisting development on a particular platform. Where it is technically
      feasable and sensible to do so however, our support libraries aim to provide platform independent APIs, and should always keep any references to
      non-platform third party libraries hidden internally, so that our application doesn't become tightly coupled to third party APIs over which we
      have no control.
    </Paragraph>
  </Section>
  <Section Title="Support Libraries">
    <PageRefList>
      <PageRefListEntry PageName="SupportLibraries.AudioStream">AudioStream</PageRefListEntry>
      <PageRefListEntry PageName="SupportLibraries.CallbackSupport">CallbackSupport</PageRefListEntry>
      <PageRefListEntry PageName="SupportLibraries.DataConversion">DataConversion</PageRefListEntry>
      <PageRefListEntry PageName="SupportLibraries.Debug">Debug</PageRefListEntry>
      <PageRefListEntry PageName="SupportLibraries.HierarchicalStorage">HierarchicalStorage</PageRefListEntry>
      <PageRefListEntry PageName="SupportLibraries.Image">Image</PageRefListEntry>
      <PageRefListEntry PageName="SupportLibraries.MarshalSupport">MarshalSupport</PageRefListEntry>
      <PageRefListEntry PageName="SupportLibraries.Stream">Stream</PageRefListEntry>
      <PageRefListEntry PageName="SupportLibraries.ThinContainers">ThinContainers</PageRefListEntry>
      <PageRefListEntry PageName="SupportLibraries.ThreadLib">ThreadLib</PageRefListEntry>
      <PageRefListEntry PageName="SupportLibraries.WindowsControls">WindowsControls</PageRefListEntry>
      <PageRefListEntry PageName="SupportLibraries.WindowsSupport">WindowsSupport</PageRefListEntry>
      <PageRefListEntry PageName="SupportLibraries.ZIP">ZIP</PageRefListEntry>
    </PageRefList>
  </Section>
</XMLDocContent>
