<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<XMLDocContent PageName="ExodusSDK.DeviceInterface.IDevice.ExecuteStep" Title="ExecuteStep method" xmlns="http://www.exodusemulator.com/schema/XMLDocSchema.xsd">
  <Section Title="Description">
    <Paragraph>
      The ExecuteStep method is called during system execution for a device that has returned the "Step" execution method from
      <PageRef PageName="ExodusSDK.DeviceInterface.IDevice.GetUpdateMethod">GetUpdateMethod</PageRef>. When this method is called, the
      device should perform whatever logic is necessary to advance the device by the smallest indivisible operation step that device supports. This
      may mean advancing the device by a single internal cycle, or for a series of operations which are carried out in sequence which cannot be
      interrupted or altered by any external event.
    </Paragraph>
    <Paragraph>
      This device must return a double value, which is the total time the device advanced in nanoseconds by the step the device just performed. This
      amount will be automatically added to the accumulated total of time advanced reported by the <PageRef PageName="ExodusSDK.DeviceInterface.IDevice.GetCurrentTimesliceProgress">GetCurrentTimesliceProgress</PageRef>
      method. When the device reaches or passes the total amount of time allocated to the device in the current timeslice, the ExecuteStep method will
      no longer be called until all devices complete the timeslice, and a new timeslice begins.
    </Paragraph>
  </Section>
  <Section Title="Usage">
    <Code>
      <![CDATA[virtual double ExecuteStep();]]>
    </Code>
    <SubSection Title="Return value">
      <ReturnValue Type="double">
        The total time the device advanced in the executed update step, in nanoseconds.
      </ReturnValue>
    </SubSection>
  </Section>
  <Section Title="See also">
    <PageRefList>
      <PageRefListEntry PageName="ExodusSDK.DeviceInterface.IDevice">IDevice</PageRefListEntry>
      <PageRefListEntry PageName="ExodusSDK.DeviceInterface.IDevice.GetCurrentTimesliceProgress">GetCurrentTimesliceProgress</PageRefListEntry>
    </PageRefList>
  </Section>
</XMLDocContent>
