<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<XMLDocContent PageName="SupportLibraries.MarshalSupport" Title="MarshalSupport Support Library" xmlns="http://www.exodusemulator.com/schema/XMLDocSchema.xsd">
  <Section Title="Description">
    <Paragraph>
      The MarshalSupport library is an advanced library which provides easy, and in most cases transparent, exchange of objects between assemblies in
      C++, even if the sender and receiver represent the object differently. This library is particularly good for sending STL objects, or custom
      types that contain STL objects, across pure virtual interfaces that are being exchanged between assemblies. This is something that is extremely
      difficult to achieve in C++, and that the language provides no support for. The MarshalSupport library solves this problem comprehensively for
      any C++03 conformant compiler onwards, and allows exchange of any types between assemblies over pure virtual interfaces, where the assemblies
      support at least enough ABI compatibility to exchange pure virtual interfaces.
    </Paragraph>
  </Section>

  <Section Title="Public Members">
    <SubSection Title="Marshal Operators">
      <PageRefList>
        <PageRefListEntry PageName="SupportLibraries.MarshalSupport.MarshalIn">Marshal::In</PageRefListEntry>
        <PageRefListEntry PageName="SupportLibraries.MarshalSupport.MarshalOut">Marshal::Out</PageRefListEntry>
        <PageRefListEntry PageName="SupportLibraries.MarshalSupport.MarshalInOut">Marshal::InOut</PageRefListEntry>
        <PageRefListEntry PageName="SupportLibraries.MarshalSupport.MarshalRet">Marshal::Ret</PageRefListEntry>
      </PageRefList>
    </SubSection>
    <SubSection Title="Marshal Classes">
      <PageRefList>
        <PageRefListEntry PageName="SupportLibraries.MarshalSupport.IMarshalSource">IMarshalSource</PageRefListEntry>
        <PageRefListEntry PageName="SupportLibraries.MarshalSupport.IMarshalTarget">IMarshalTarget</PageRefListEntry>
        <PageRefListEntry PageName="SupportLibraries.MarshalSupport.MarshalSource">MarshalSource</PageRefListEntry>
        <PageRefListEntry PageName="SupportLibraries.MarshalSupport.MarshalTarget">MarshalTarget</PageRefListEntry>
      </PageRefList>
    </SubSection>
  </Section>

  <Section Title="Status of the library">
    <Paragraph>
      This library is in an extremely advanced and mature state, with a high level of optimization in place, as well as extensive cross-compiler
      testing having been performed. A full set of unit tests has also been developed. This library is considered stable and available for use in all
      areas of code.
    </Paragraph>
    <Paragraph>
      The only planned future changes to this library are to add support for new container types. Full support for C++11 container types is provided
      currently, with the exception of std::pair and std::tuple, both of which we should support in the future. The C++14 standards and onwards have
      not been considered yet.
    </Paragraph>
  </Section>
</XMLDocContent>
