<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<XMLDocContent PageName="SupportLibraries.DataConversion" Title="DataConversion Support Library" xmlns="http://www.exodusemulator.com/schema/XMLDocSchema.xsd" xmlns:doc="http://www.exodusemulator.com/schema/XMLDocSchema.xsd">
  <Section Title="Description">
    <Paragraph>
      The DataConversion library provides a set of general conversion routines to and from text for integers, floating point, and boolean types. The
      library also provides some text to text conversion routines. All conversion functions adopt the same conventions, which makes it easy to convert
      betwen types and understand what the output of various conversions will be.
    </Paragraph>
    <Paragraph>
      All integer conversion functions support a unified prefix notation for distinguising the base encoding of any arbitrary number from a string.
      These prefixes are adopted based on the prevailing conventions used in various programming languages and markup systems. Only one prefix is used
      when converting to a string, but when loading from a string, several forms are permitted. The following list shows the list of supported
      prefixes for converting integers from strings. The prefix used for saving to string is the first one shown for each base encoding.
    </Paragraph>
    <Code>Base 16: 0x????, 0X????, 0h????, 0H????
Base 10: 0d????, 0D????
Base 8:  0o????, 0O????, 0q????, 0Q????
Base 2:  0b????, 0B????</Code>
    <Paragraph>
      Note that we don't support any postfix base encoding forms, because they can be ambiguous with unqualified number encodings from other bases.
      Using the 'b' and 'd' characters in particular as postfixes would conflict with base 16 encoding, but other encoding schemes like base 32
      encoding that could be added later would conflict with all postfixes. There are various other language conventions that have also been rejected,
      such as a leading '0' in C++ representing a base 8 number. Using the prefixes that have been specified, it is always safe to evaluate qualified
      or non-fixed length unqualified strings containing integers.
    </Paragraph>
  </Section>

  <Section Title="Public Members">
    <SubSection Title="Boolean Conversion">
      <FunctionMemberList>
        <FunctionMemberListEntry Visibility="Public" Name="BoolToString">
          Converts a boolean into a string in the requested form
        </FunctionMemberListEntry>
        <FunctionMemberListEntry Visibility="Public" Name="StringToBool">
          Attempts to convert a string into a boolean
        </FunctionMemberListEntry>
      </FunctionMemberList>
    </SubSection>
    <SubSection Title="Integer Conversion">
      <FunctionMemberList>
        <FunctionMemberListEntry Visibility="Public" Name="HexNybbleToChar">
          Converts an integer of the range 0x0-0xF to a corresponding hexadecimal char
        </FunctionMemberListEntry>
        <FunctionMemberListEntry Visibility="Public" Name="HexNybbleToWChar">
          Converts an integer of the range 0x0-0xF to a corresponding hexadecimal wchar_t
        </FunctionMemberListEntry>
        <FunctionMemberListEntry Visibility="Public" Name="HexCharToNybble">
          Converts a hexadecimal digit from a char into an integer of the range 0x0-0xF, or 0x10 if the specified character is not a hexadecimal digit.
        </FunctionMemberListEntry>
        <FunctionMemberListEntry Visibility="Public" Name="HexWCharToNybble">
          Converts a hexadecimal digit from a wchar_t into an integer of the range 0x0-0xF, or 0x10 if the specified character is not a hexadecimal digit.
        </FunctionMemberListEntry>
        <FunctionMemberListEntry Visibility="Public" Name="IntToString">
          Converts an integer into a string, using the specified base encoding.
        </FunctionMemberListEntry>
        <FunctionMemberListEntry Visibility="Public" Name="IntToStringBase16">
          Converts an integer into a base 16 string, with control over type encoding and length.
        </FunctionMemberListEntry>
        <FunctionMemberListEntry Visibility="Public" Name="IntToStringBase10">
          Converts an integer into a base 10 string, with control over type encoding and length.
        </FunctionMemberListEntry>
        <FunctionMemberListEntry Visibility="Public" Name="IntToStringBase8">
          Converts an integer into a base 8 string, with control over type encoding and length.
        </FunctionMemberListEntry>
        <FunctionMemberListEntry Visibility="Public" Name="IntToStringBase2">
          Converts an integer into a base 2 string, with control over type encoding and length.
        </FunctionMemberListEntry>
        <FunctionMemberListEntry Visibility="Public" Name="StringToInt">
          Attempts to convert a string into an integer, using the specified default base encoding if it isn't specified in the string.
        </FunctionMemberListEntry>
        <FunctionMemberListEntry Visibility="Public" Name="StringToIntBase16">
          Attempts to convert a base 16 number as a string into an integer
        </FunctionMemberListEntry>
        <FunctionMemberListEntry Visibility="Public" Name="StringToIntBase10">
          Attempts to convert a base 10 number as a string into an integer
        </FunctionMemberListEntry>
        <FunctionMemberListEntry Visibility="Public" Name="StringToIntBase8">
          Attempts to convert a base 8 number as a string into an integer
        </FunctionMemberListEntry>
        <FunctionMemberListEntry Visibility="Public" Name="StringToIntBase2">
          Attempts to convert a base 2 number as a string into an integer
        </FunctionMemberListEntry>
      </FunctionMemberList>
    </SubSection>
    <SubSection Title="Floating Point Conversion">
      <FunctionMemberList>
        <FunctionMemberListEntry Visibility="Public" Name="FloatToString">
          Converts a single precision floating point number into a string in the requested form
        </FunctionMemberListEntry>
        <FunctionMemberListEntry Visibility="Public" Name="StringToFloat">
          Attempts to convert a string into a single precision floating point number
        </FunctionMemberListEntry>
        <FunctionMemberListEntry Visibility="Public" Name="DoubleToString">
          Converts a double precision floating point number into a string in the requested form
        </FunctionMemberListEntry>
        <FunctionMemberListEntry Visibility="Public" Name="StringToDouble">
          Attempts to convert a string into a double precision floating point number
        </FunctionMemberListEntry>
      </FunctionMemberList>
    </SubSection>
    <SubSection Title="String Conversion">
      <FunctionMemberList>
        <FunctionMemberListEntry Visibility="Public" Name="TokenizeString">
          Tokenizes the supplied string using the set of specified delimiter characters
        </FunctionMemberListEntry>
        <FunctionMemberListEntry Visibility="Public" Name="CharToLower">
          Converts the target ASCII character to its lowercase equivalent. This function does not attempt to support Unicode characters.
        </FunctionMemberListEntry>
        <FunctionMemberListEntry Visibility="Public" Name="CharToUpper">
          Converts the target ASCII character to its uppercase equivalent. This function does not attempt to support Unicode characters.
        </FunctionMemberListEntry>
        <FunctionMemberListEntry Visibility="Public" Name="StringToLower">
          Converts all ASCII characters in the target string to their lowercase equivalent. This function does not attempt to support Unicode characters.
        </FunctionMemberListEntry>
        <FunctionMemberListEntry Visibility="Public" Name="StringToUpper">
          Converts all ASCII characters in the target string to their uppercase equivalent. This function does not attempt to support Unicode characters.
        </FunctionMemberListEntry>
        <FunctionMemberListEntry Visibility="Public" Name="StringToWString">
          Converts an std::string with ASCII encoding to an std::wstring. This function does not attempt to support non-ASCII characters.
        </FunctionMemberListEntry>
        <FunctionMemberListEntry Visibility="Public" Name="WStringToString">
          Converts an std::wstring with ASCII encoding to an std::string. This function does not attempt to support non-ASCII characters.
        </FunctionMemberListEntry>
      </FunctionMemberList>
    </SubSection>
  </Section>

  <Section Title="Status of the library">
    <Paragraph>
      This library originally grew as required, however it is now quite consistent in its use. There are some limitations regarding the output of
      floating point numbers at fixed lengths however, and these cannot be worked around without a major investment of work, due to limits of control
      around how both std::stringstream and printf perform floating point conversion. These issues will be fixed if they cause problems in the future.
    </Paragraph>
    <Paragraph>
      Note that although what is currently in this library is fairly good, the library itself is not considered feature complete. There are many other
      conversion functions that may be added in the future as a need for them arises.
    </Paragraph>
  </Section>
</XMLDocContent>
