<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<XMLDocContent PageName="SupportLibraries.HierarchicalStorage" Title="HierarchicalStorage Support Library" xmlns="http://www.exodusemulator.com/schema/XMLDocSchema.xsd">
  <Section Title="Description">
    <Paragraph>
      The HierarchicalStorage library is designed to support an abstract representation of a hierarchical data structure, where each node on the
      hierarchy can potentially contain child nodes, as well as an unlimited number of attributes in the form of a key/value pair, and a single block
      of arbitrary data associated with the nodes. This library allows a structure like this to be created, edited, saved, and loaded.
    </Paragraph>
    <Paragraph>
      The primary input and output format of the HierarchicalStorage library is XML. Support for other formats has been considered in the design of
      the library however, and new input and output formats can easily be added without breaking compatibility with existing code.
    </Paragraph>
    <Paragraph>
      This library is split into two halves, HierarchicalStorage and HierarchicalStorageInterface. This allows code which only needs to use these
      structures, not create the initial root definition of the structure itself, to include only the header files required to work with the
      structure. This reduces code linkage, encourages the use of the interface base types, and reduces compilation types and assembly sizes.
    </Paragraph>
  </Section>

  <Section Title="Public Members">
    <SubSection Title="HierarchicalStorageInterface Members">
      <PageRefList>
        <PageRefListEntry PageName="SupportLibraries.HierarchicalStorage.IHierarchicalStorageTree">IHierarchicalStorageTree</PageRefListEntry>
        <PageRefListEntry PageName="SupportLibraries.HierarchicalStorage.IHierarchicalStorageNode">IHierarchicalStorageNode</PageRefListEntry>
        <PageRefListEntry PageName="SupportLibraries.HierarchicalStorage.IHierarchicalStorageAttribute">IHierarchicalStorageAttribute</PageRefListEntry>
      </PageRefList>
    </SubSection>
    <SubSection Title="HierarchicalStorage Members">
      <PageRefList>
        <PageRefListEntry PageName="SupportLibraries.HierarchicalStorage.HierarchicalStorageTree">HierarchicalStorageTree</PageRefListEntry>
        <PageRefListEntry PageName="SupportLibraries.HierarchicalStorage.HierarchicalStorageNode">HierarchicalStorageNode</PageRefListEntry>
        <PageRefListEntry PageName="SupportLibraries.HierarchicalStorage.HierarchicalStorageAttribute">HierarchicalStorageAttribute</PageRefListEntry>
      </PageRefList>
    </SubSection>
  </Section>

  <Section Title="Status of the library">
    <Paragraph>
      This library is considered stable and complete. If support for more storage formats is desired in the future, extensions may be made to the
      library to implement that support, however this should not impact existing use.
    </Paragraph>
  </Section>
</XMLDocContent>
